An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society 1799-1882 Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
- Calendar of Letters
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860 June] 14th [wmk. 1860]; 216; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 5p. and 1p. enc. @ 4.5 x7.25 (other enclosures wanting)
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 319-20. At beginning of letter is: Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield] is in slightly worse health; CD cannot walk; sends extract of letter from [Edward] Blyth, who is grateful to Lyell for help concerning Chinese expedition; 1 encloses letter from [William] Hopkins; fancies Hopkins is "horrified about man; I have told him that I thought man must be included under same category with animals"; returns four pamphlets; does not see much in Binney [see previous letter, above]. p. 319, line 5, add: "It is no wonder [Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz denies varieties in animals, when he calls even the same forms in two distinct countries, two Species." At end of letter is: after much puzzling, does not know what A[ndrew] Murray meant [see CD to Lyell, June 1, 1860, above] by "Agassiz & ab ovo". End. reads: Blyth says there is account of flint tools found in ice in [Elizabeth Juliana Leeves] Sabine's translation of [Ferdinand Petrovich, Baron von] Wrangell's [i.e. Vrangel's] Voyage 2 on page 117 of introduction; this find relates to issues like mastodon found in ice, and is worth checking; Blyth thinks Eskimos, when first discovered, had no iron tools, and he refers to essay 3 by J[ohn] Richardson.
    1. See the following letters, all abstracted above: CD to W. H. Sykes, December 20, 1859; CD to Lyell, December 29, 1859; and CD to Lyell, late March-early April, 1860. See also Loren C. Eiseley, "Charles Darwin, Edward Blyth, and the Theory of Natural Selection," Proc. Am. phil. Soc., 103 (1959): 154-55.
    2. Narrative of an Expedition to the Polar Sea..., tr.... by Mrs. Sabine, ed. by E. Sabine (London: J. Madden and Co., 1840).
    3. "Esquimaux: Their Geographical Distribution," Edinb. new phil. J., 52 (1852), 322-23.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] June 17th [wmk. 1860]; 217; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 4p.
    Printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: More Letters, I, 154 (letter 105). line 24, add: Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield] is slightly better in health, has been ill for exactly seven weeks.
  - To [Thomas Campbell] EYTON; Down (type 2), [1860]; 218; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 1p.
    Please send to CD any authentic cases of duration of gestation in dogs; hounds, otter-hounds, or any breed will be acceptable.
    1. Portion of a watermark on this letter appears to be 1860. Also, dimensions of stationery and Down address used fit a dating of 1860. Finally, CD was studying gestation of dogs for the first time in June, 1860; see CD to Charles Lyell, June 1, 1860, above.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860 June] 20th [wmk. 1860]; 219; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 4p.
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 155-56 (letter 106). p. 155, line 8, change "surely we" to "surely as we".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860 June] 25th [wmk. 1860]; 220; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 4p. (enclosures wanting)
    Printed, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 155n. At beginning of letter is: encloses authentic arrowheads, with note describing location of discovery, which were sent to CD by Mrs. Moir, mother-in-law of Col. Erskine. 1 line 4, questionable word is definitely "record". At end of letter is: because of bad stomach, will give up, reluctantly, his plans to attend [B.A.A.S. meeting at] Oxford [June 27-July 4]; will leave Thursday [June 28] for one week of water cure at Dr. [Richard James] Lane's, Sudbrook Park, Richmond, Surrey; will not stay longer because Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter], while better, is still ill; thanks for letter just received; returns unimpressive letter from [John William] Dawson; 2 wishes to borrow Dawson's review [of Darwin, Origin (1859)]; on Dawson's letter, it "would be insanity to compare evidence of organic change with geological change, at present, as far as strength of evidence goes. But what inches of elevation on coast of Sweden are to great mountains so are the numerous varieties & endless doubts what to call species & what varieties, to undoubted species. I entirely deny that there is no evidence of change. But time alone will bring naturalists round, when they find that they can explain many facts on such views as mine, & cannot on view of creation."
    1. See CD to Lyell, May 4, 1860, above.
    2. For Lyell's comments on Dawson's letter, see Leonard G. Wilson, ed., Sir Charles Lyell's Scientific Journals on the Species Question (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1970), 457-58.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Sudbrook Park/ Richmond, [1860 July] 5th. Thursday [wmk. 1860]; 221; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 4p., plus 1p. fragment of AD by Lyell @ 6 x5 Fragment removed + Carroll no. 172
    Thanks for note; glad Lyell is going to Amiens; while there, please explain high and low dispersion of flint gravel; also glad Lyell to investigate post-glacial period; Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] moved to Hartfield on Tuesday; leaves on Saturday; glad CD did not attempt [B.A.A.S. meeting at] Oxford; "[Thomas Henry] Huxley, [Joseph Dalton] Hooker & J[ohn] Lubbock (as I am pleased to hear) seem to have stuck up for modification of Species like Trojans"; Asa Gray also goes on fighting for CD's theory; 1 thinks "we shall in long run conquer"; likes [article by William] Hopkins in Fraser's Magazine, 2 but regrets "soul-discussion"; difficulties alone " make a very damaging review"; Lyell's facts convinced CD for first time that hare-rabbits are hybrids; could not confirm this before. 3 Enc. is entitled "C. Darwin/ On Species & Creation" and is merely a list of such headings as "Bermuda & Madeira Birds why like Continental--" and "Primrose & cowslip".
    1.?See Historical Records Survey, Division of Professional and Service Projects, Works Projects Administration, Calendar of the Letters of Charles Robert Darwin to Asa Gray (Boston: Historical Records Survey, 1939; reprinted Wilmington, Delaware: Scholarly Resources, Inc., 1973), 27-28.
    2. "Physical Theories of the Phenomena of Life," 61 (1860): 739-52; and 62 (1860): 74-90.
    3. See: CD to Lyell, May 18, 1860, above; CD to Lyell, May 22, 1860, above; and Darwin, Variation under Domestication (1868), I, 105 and 105n.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Hartfield, [1860] July 30th; 222; ALS; 10.5 x8.25 2p.
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 327-28. At beginning of letter is: have been at Hartfield three weeks because Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] is still ill; return home in few days [August 2]; H[enry] Holland saw Etty few days ago, predicted long recovery; has seen no one except [Joseph Dalton] Hooker for hour or two at Kew. p. 327, line 9, add: "considering [Richard] Owen's aid [by the way it seems generally admitted that Huxley smashed Owen at Oxford] 1 [CD brackets]; it quizzes me really in capital style". p. 328, line 3, missing name is "Owen". p. 328, line 5, add: "Owen is really wonderfully clever in his malevolence."
    1. Reference is to Thomas Henry Huxley at the B.A.A.S. meeting at Oxford from June 27 to July 4, 1860.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] August 11th; 223; ALS; 10.5 x8.25 4p.
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 331-32. At beginning of letter is: thanks for letter; have been home about a week; Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] improving, but anxiety over her has interrupted CD's work. p. 331, line 11, missing name is [Richard] Owen. p. 331, line 14, add: A[sa] Gray "argued capitally" for CD at second discussion [of natural selection] before American Academy [of Arts and Sciences]; Owen sent copy of "one of his Reports, so he does not wish to come to quarrel with me." p. 331, line 20, add: Rudolf Wagner has published in Germany an abstract of [Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz, [ An] Essay on Classification [London: Longman & Co., 1859] in relation to `Darwin ansichten' and concludes that truth lies between CD and Agassiz, which "will make Agassiz savage"; [Thomas Henry] Huxley says [Karl Ernst Ritter] Von [ sic; von] Baer [Edler von Huthorn] "goes a long way with us,...has spoken publicly &...will perhaps publish on subject." p. 331, line 24, add: there is a very good, geological, favorable third article [on natural selection] in London [Quarterly and Holborn] Review, author unknown. p. 332, line 7, add: Mrs. [Frances Harriet Henslow] H[ooker] and baby [Brian Harvey Hodgson Hooker] are at Worthing; latter is ill.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Aug 28th; 224; ALS; 10.5 x8.25 2p.
    While in London lately, heard that Sir G[eorge] Grey found his wife [Harriet Spencer Grey] in bed with "Capt. Keppell"; saw [Hugh] Falconer, who spoke of "tiny new species of Elephant from Malta"; Asa Gray's review [i.e. part two of "Darwin on the Origin of Species"] in August Atlantic Monthly [6 (1860): 229-39] is excellent, argumentative; 1 Gray is "a first rate arguer" who "most completely understands the subject"; CD has been abused in Catholic journal; glad that "Rajah Sir J[ames] Brook" is well again; work going well, today finished dogs; 2 still believes dogs descended from "several wild stocks"; sent Athenaeum and Quarterly Review.
    1. For a recent reprint and a full publication history of this review, see Asa Gray, Darwiniana..., ed. A. Hunter Dupree (Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press, 1963), 72n and 85-105.
    2. Darwin, Variation under Domestication (1868), I, 15-43.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Sept. 1.; 225; ALS; 10.5 x8.25 4p.
    Printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters II, 334-37. p. 336, line 22, after "applies", add "perhaps". p. 336, line 29, change "clear" to "close".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Sept. 12th; 226; ALS; 10.5 x8.25 4p.
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 339-41. p. 339, line 5, add: "Even if his mind had not been full of [thoughts about his trip to] Syria he could never have conjectured your precise line of thought." p. 340, line 13, add: cannot estimate number of species " `extinguished in a given time' "; passages on pages 168 and 313 [of Darwin, Origin (1859) or (1860)] are not contradictory, because "Mere variability & variability taken advantage of & selected are widely different considerations"; gives example of rudimentary organs; has not been guarded enough in claim that Ammonites became extinct relatively suddenly compared to other families [see Origin, 321-22]; has alluded to much extinction and modification in great intervals between formations; thinks it striking that in southern Chile near Concepcion, there are apparently Tertiary beds with Ammonites and Baculites. p. 341, line 7, add: Darwins go to sea [Eastbourne] in about a week [Sept. 22]. 1
    1. For Lyell's letters to CD during this period, see Leonard G. Wilson, ed., Sir Charles Lyell's Scientific Journals on the Species Question (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1970), 467-69, 472-77.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15 Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860 September] 23d Sunday; 227; ALS; 8.25 x6.5 10p. and 2 sketches
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 341-44. p. 341, line 6, add: has sent review by A[sa] Gray; 1 as Ann. Mag. nat. Hist. has printed [Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz's article, 2 will ask its editor [William Jardine] in fairness to reprint Gray at CD's expense and with Gray's name attached; Gray's review good because it gives so much of [Francois Jules] Pictet [de la Rive]; "The Annals, I fear, have very small circulation"; misunderstood Lyell on types; mentions health of Etty [Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] and death of the [Thomas Henry] Huxleys's son [Noel Huxley]. p. 342, lines 12 to 14, add in left margin: "[Richard] Owen if he chose to attend to such view could work this out." p. 342, line 20, add: was silent because unsure that there was fossil rodent in Australia, but thought not; as to Australia's especial suitability for marsupials, "I have always thought it a gigantic hallucination of Owen.--not to mention Rodents"; dingo was wild long before South Australian volcanic outburst, and there are many marsupial species in Brazil; also, New Guinea, although humid, is tenanted by marsupials as exclusively as Australia; despite antiquity of dingo (referred to in dog MS 3), thinks dingo introduced by man, and if so, this bears on antiquity of man; if dingo existed outside Australia then it is not aboriginal in Australia; [René Primevère] Lesson says same about dog of New Ireland, but Lesson not to be trusted; likes case of tree stump living by natural grafting of roots, wants reference on it; thinks case confined to Coniferae. 4 p. 342, line 27, add: [Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz's remark in [Josiah Clark] Nott and [George Robins] Gliddon 5 on coincidence of color alone being a fleeting character "does not go for much in his comparison of man & anthropoid apes."
    1. See CD to Lyell, August 28, 1860, above.
    2. "Prof. Agassiz on the Origin of Species," Ann. Mag. nat. Hist., 6 (1860): 219-32.
    3. Darwin, Variation under Domestication (1868), I, 15-43, in manuscript.
    4. See also Leonard G. Wilson, ed., Sir Charles Lyell's Scientific Journals on the Species Question (New Haven; Yale Univ. Press, 1970), 476.
    5. Louis Agassiz, "Sketch of the Natural Provinces of the Animal World and Their Relation to the Different Types of Man," in J. C. Nott and G. R. Gliddon, Types of Mankind; Or Ethnological Researches... (Philadelphia: Lippincott, Grambo & Co., 1854), lxxv.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15 Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860 September] 26th [wmk. 1860]; 228; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 8p.
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 167-69 (letter 112).
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15. Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860 September] 28 Friday Evening [wmk. 1860]; 229; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 8p. (slightly mutilated)
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 345-46. At beginning of letter is: mentions Lyell's letter; extinction of Ammonites is "a most singular fact" despite what Lyell says about great breaks in upper chalk; Lyell may obtain Atlantic Monthly at Trubners. p. 345, line 6, add: "but in very difficult points, &". p. 346, line 2, add: has asked A[sa] Gray where [Karl Ernst Ritter] Von [ sic; von] Baer [Edler von Huthorn] makes statement about guinea pig, which is worthless unless there is new evidence about wild parent; denies that aperea of La Plata and southern Brazil is the wild parent stock; guinea pig was domesticated when America was discovered; von Baer has read [Darwin, Origin (1859)] approvingly; would keep [?i.e. breed] hybrid hare-rabbit himself, but still would not have evidence of hybridity of any specimens obtained from France; [Abraham Dee] Bartlett is correct to try to cross wild hare and rabbit, but he should try several races of rabbit.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15 Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860] Oct. 3d [wmk. 1860]; 230; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 11p.
    Printed, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 169-72 (letter 113). p. 169, line 1, add: "The Dog MS is safe at Down." p. 171, line 37, add: Lyell's remarks on Ammonites, cuttlefish, and Hippurites are interesting; 1 will think about keeping the rabbits; Isidore G[eoffroy] S[ain]t Hilaire, of whom CD has very good opinion, only knows the case second hand; [Richard] Owen "sneers at [Geoffroy Saint Hillaire]; & I daresay he [?] is not [to] be trusted on Homologies"; 2 do not trust Sclagenweit [i.e. Hermann Rudolf Alfred von Schlagintweit-Sakünlünski and Robert von Schlagintweit] about yaks; 3 "there are many reputed species (laying on one side question of fertility) not so distinct as negro & white man."
    1. See Leonard G. Wilson, ed., Sir Charles Lyell's Scientific Journals on the Species Question (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1970), 497.
    2. For Geoffroy Saint Hilaire on homologies, see Stauffer, ed., CD's Nat. Selection, 298 and 298n.
    3. Hermann and Robert Schlagintweit, "Notes on Some of the Animals of Tibet and India," Rep. Br. Ass. Advmnt Sci., 27 (1857), pt. 2: 106-08. See also Stauffer, ed., CD's Nat. Selection, 438 and 438n.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15 Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860 October] 5th Friday [wmk. 1860]; 231; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 6p.
    Printed, with minor changes: More Letters, I, 172 (letter 114). line 8, change "creative" to "creation". At end of letter is: bats are "washed out of my head"; species in Madeira, collected by Mr. Mason [?], are European; does not remember about Palma specimens, given to [Robert Fisher] Tomes of Welford; did not get Azores species; "I had heard nothing of the sales of `Origin' [i.e. Darwin, Origin] for months, & am much pleased to hear that the sale continues; this surprises me"; has not received second Atnaltic article, 1 meant for [Francois Jules] Pictet [de la Rive]; has not received theological dialogue; 2 [Hugh] Falconer, who is only man who has facts correct, is critical of Isidore Geoffroy [Saint Hilaire]; will check on St. Helena concerning [? Geoffroy St. Hilaire's] conjecture about number of plants exterminated; St. Helena was woody in late periods; see Darwin, Journal of Researches; is "wasting time shamefully" on Drosera experiments which are "perverse & crooked"; Etty [i.e. Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] is gaining strength; [Heinrich Georg] Bronn has appended chapter of objections at end of translation; 3 Miss Ludwig has translated it for CD.
    1. Asa Gray, "Darwin on the Origin of Species [Part II]," Atlantic Monthly, 6 (1860): 229-39. See CD to Lyell, Aug. 28, 1860, above.
    2. "Discussion between Two Readers of Darwin's Treatise on the Origin of Species, upon Its Natural Theology," Am. J. Sci. (Silliman's J.), 30 (1860): 226-39.
    3. Darwin, Über die Entstehung der Arten... [German Origin], tr. into German by H. G. Bronn (Stuttgart; Schweizerbart'sche Verlag, 1860).
  - To [Charles] LYELL; 15 Marine Parade/ Eastbourne, [1860] Oct 8. [wmk. 1860]; 232; ALS; 7 3/4 x5; 6p. and 1p. enc. [broadside advertisement for C. R. Bree, Species Not Transmutable,...(London: Groombridge and Sons, 1860)], @ 7.5 x5
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 346-47. p. 347, line 19, add: has written to Down about missing reviews [see preceding letter, above]; believes southeast and southwest corners of Australia were islands, with latter older and more typical; [Joseph Dalton] Hooker has speculated on this in Introduction; 1 so have [Joseph Beete] Jukes and CD himself in review 2 of [George Robert] Waterhouse's [A Natural History of the] Mammalia [2v. (London: H. Ballière, 1846-1848)]; in Saturday's Athenaeum, Jukes answered capitally Sir [Henry] James's "wild speculations" on change of earth's axis. 3 p. 347, line 24, add: Miss L[udwig] says [Heinrich Georg] Bronn is very difficult German [see preceding letter, above]; has not heard of Bovey Coal Plants; 4 hopes [Charles James Fox] Bunbury will undertake them and that Bunbury's new position will not interfere with his science; does not know [Charles Robert] Bree, perhaps the son of Rev[eren]d [William Thomas] Bree, "a good miscellaneous observer of habits of all creatures...& Botanist."
    1. See CD to Lyell, Sept. 2, 1859, above, esp. my note 2.
    2. Ann. Mag. nat. Hist., 19 (1847): 53-56, esp. top of 56.
    3. See More Letters, II, 140n.
    4. See Life of Lyell, II, 346-47 and 349-50.
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Nov. 20; 233; ALS; 8.25 x6.5 4p. and 4p. enc.
    First portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions; More Letters, I, 461 (letter 351). At end of this portion is: Lyell's chapters must be difficult but are worth much labor; fears that Lyell's volume on geological history of man [i.e. The Geological Evidences of the Antiquity of Man (London: John Murray, 1863)] "will slip through your fingers"; does not think [Joseph Dalton] Hooker has criticized [Edward] Forbes; H[ewett] C[ottrell] Watson has abused Forbes in Cybele [ Britannica; Or, British Plants and Their Geographical Relations, 4v. (London: Longman & Co., 1847-1852), I, 465-72], but it is not well done. Next portion and enclosure printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters II, 349-51. p. 350, after signature, add: Etty [i.e. Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] goes on well, but is weak. p. 350, right column of enclosure, line 3, change "alludes to" to "attacks".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Nov. 24th [wmk. 1859]; 234; ALS; 4p. @ 8 x5, 2p. @ 8 3/4 x5.5 6p.
    First portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters II, 352, lines 1 to 10.
    Next portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters III, 319-20. At end of this portion is: Etty [i.e. Henrietta Emma Darwin Litchfield, CD's daughter] goes on well, but doctors say rapid progress is impossible; Drosera and dreadful illness for last six months has made progress on CD's larger book "almost nothing".
    Next portion printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 352-53, beginning where first portion ended. p. 352, line 4 of this portion, missing name is "[Richard] Owen".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Nov. 25th; 235; ALS; 8.25 x6.5 6p.
    Printed in full, with minor changes: More Letters, II, 137-40 (letter 491). p. 139, line 29, change "the great" to "that great [an]".
  - To [Charles] LYELL; Down (type 2), [1860] Dec. 4th; 236; ALS; 8 x6.5 5p.
    First portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: More Letters, II, 140-41 (letter 492). p. 141, line 10, add: "How far to lump & split species is indeed a hopeless problem. It must in the end, I think, be determined by mere convenience." At end of this portion is: glad to hear that Lyell continues to "stir them up" at Zoolog[ical] Soc[iety of London].
    Next portion printed, with minor changes and minor omissions: Life and Letters II, 352n. At end of this portion is: there is an article 1 on Darwin, Origin, in Macmillan's Magazine; has not yet read [John] Phillips, [ Life on the Earth, Its Origin and Succession (Cambridge: Macmillan and Co., 1860)].
    1. Henry Fawcett, "A Popular Exposition of Mr. Darwin on the Origin of Species," 3 (December, 1860): 81-92. For a recent reprinting, see David L. Hull, Darwin and His Critics: The Reception of Darwin's Theory of Evolution by the Scientific Community (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, 1973), 277-90. See also Life and Letters II, 299.
  - To?; Down (type 2) To: Edward Walford, [Jan-Apr. 1865]; 237; ALS; 7.5 x5; 2p.
    Would be proud to be one of their series [?of photographs of famous persons], but cannot spare time for special trip to London and is not likely to be there on business soon; will call on Mr. Edwards during the summer, when next in London.
    1. Watermark sets lower endpoint for date. Type of Down address employed was last used in 1861, which sets upper endpoint.
  - To Ch[arles] LYELL; no location, [1861] Feb. 2d [end. Febry 3d. 1861; pmk. FE 3/ 61]; 238; ALS; 8 x6.5 2p. and env., add. [Sir Ch. Lyell/ 53. Harley St/ London (W.)], end. [C. Darwin/ Febry 3d. 1861; C. Darwin/ Feb. 1861/ Agassiz &/ Bowen/ (unintelligible word--PTC)]
    Printed in full, with minor changes: Life and Letters II, 359-60. p. 359, line 6, change "the lengths" to "the very absurd lengths". p. 359, line 13, change "[Jean Louis Rodolphe] Agassiz admits" to "Agassiz (foolish man) admits". At end of letter is: "I sent Calcutta Review a couple of days ago." 1
    1. [Edward Blyth], "[Review of] On the Origin of Species," Calcutta Review, 35 (1860): 64-88. See also Vorzimmer, Reprint Catalogue, item R.61.